Guide to the Papers of William Baskerville Hamilton, circa 1700-1975 RL.00495
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Pictures
  Two boxes of pictures include numerous photographs of William B. Hamilton and members of his family. Most pictures date from the twentieth century, but a few are from the nineteenth century. Scenes in Mississippi and elsewhere are also included, several of them being of Burnside, the antebellum Hamilton home near Henderson, N.C. Several engravings and copies of portraits are of English scenes and the Grenvilles. Fourteen framed engravings, mostly of English statesmen and mansions, also belong to the collection, and a list of them is filed with the pictures.
  - Pictures (Box 117-118)
- Mississippi Research
  This series includes boxes 119-128. Additional materials can be found in boxes 178 and 179.
  - Letter on Origin of Court Records (Box 119)
  - Adams County:
    - County Court Minutes (Transcripts):
      - Volume, 1802-1804, pp. 1-269 (Box 119)
      - Volume, 1804-1812, pp. 1-134 (Box 119)
      - Volume, 1804-1812, pp. 135-407 (Box 120)
      - Volume, 1804-1812, pp. 408-511 (Box 121)
      - Volume, 1804-1810, pp. 1-94 (Box 121)
      - Volume, 1812-1818, pp. 1-80 (Box 121)
      - Volume, 1812-1818, pp. 81-221 (Box 122)
      - Volume, 1818-1831, Index and pp. 1-113 (Box 122)
    - Court of Common Pleas: (Box 123)
      - Judgments and Dismissions (Transcripts):
        - Volume A, 1799-1801, pp. 1-211 (Box 123)
        - Volume A, 1799-1801, pp. 212-408 (Box 124)
        - Volume A, 1799-1801, pp. 409-552 (Box 125)
        - Volume B, 1802-1811, pp. 1-70 (Box 125)
        - Volume B, 1802-1811, pp. 71-255 (Box 126)
        - Volume B, 1802-1811, pp. 256-484 (Box 127)
    - Mayor's Court: (Box 128)
      - Judgments and Dismissions (Transcripts):
        - Volume C, 1803-1804, pp. 1-134 (Box 128)
  - Alphabetical Files, A-Z: (Box 129-135)
    Several boxes of notes and transcripts and photographic copies of manuscripts. Some folders are grouped into categories and others are simply filed alphabetically.
    - Thomas Rodney (Box 136-141)
      Several boxes of letters, journals, notebooks, legal papers, writings, and other items, mostly written by or to Rodney or pertaining to him. Mostly photographic copies of manuscripts from various libraries.
    - Notes (Box 144-148)
      Several card file boxes and drawers of notes on Mississippi history during the later decades or the 18th century, the territorial period, and, to a lesser extent, the antebellum decades, These notes have been left in their original boxes and order, and chronology and topics are not necessarily in order. Researchers should examine all these boxes.
    - Microfilm: (Box 142-143)
      The contents of a number of these reels were reproduced as prints that are filed mostly in the Thomas Rodney section and occasionally in the alphabetical section.
      - Manuscripts, 1797-1807, of Winthrop Sargent. No source. Negative. (Box 142, Reel 1)
      - Thomas Rodney, Accounts, 1803-1810, No source, Negative. (Box 142, Reel 2)
      - Thomas Rodney, Court Notebooks, 1806-1809, Library of Congress. Negative. (Box 142, Reel 3)
      - Manuscripts, 1800-1809, from the Thomas Jefferson, James Madison, and Thomas Rodney papers in the Library of Congress. Negative. (Box 142, Reel 4)
      - John Francis Hamtramck Claiborne's diaries, recollections, etc.,1820's-1840's. Thomas Rodney letters, 1804-1807, Library of Congress. Negative. (Box 142, Reel 5)
      - Wailes' Extracts from [William] Dunbar's Letter Book, 1775-1803, No source, Negative. (Box 142, Reel 6)
      - Journal of Thomas Rodney kept on trip from Dover, Delaware, through Pennsylvania and down Mississippi River, Aug.-Oct., 1803. Library of Congress, Negative. (Box 142, Reel 7)
      - Thomas Rodney, Court Notebooks, 1804-1805 and 1807. Library of Congress. Negative. (Box 142, Reel 8)
      - Manuscripts, 1804-1808, from the Thomas Jefferson and Thomas Rodney papers in the Library of Congress. Negative. (Box 143, Reel 9)
      - Manuscripts, 1798-1811, from James Madison and possibly other collections at the Library of Congress. Negative. (Box 143, Reel 10)
      - Miscellaneous Scraps of Legal Dicta Rodney. Library of Congress. I have enlarged Prints. Film left in original box. Negative. (Box 143, Reel 11)
      - Personal Tax Rolls, Mississippi Territory. Roll #299. Adams County, 1802, through Jefferson County, 1812. Positive. (Box 143, Reel 12)
      - Personal Tax Rolls, Mississippi Territory. Roll #300. Jefferson County, 1813, through Wilkinson County, 1817. Positive. (Box 143, Reel 13)
- Grenville Research
  - Boconnoc, Cornwall: (Box 149)
    - Correspondence, 1803-1828 (Box 149)
    - Correspondence possibly from Boconnoc, 1792-1828 and undated (Box 149)
    - Lord Grenville's Commentaries of My Own Political Life and of Public Transactions Connected With It (Box 150)
      A copy of this manuscript can be found on reel 16 of Grenville Research Microfilm, box 153.
  - Miscellaneous Sources and Materials: (Box 151)
    - Bucks Record Office:
      - A.R. 30/63, 1792-1845 (Box 151)
      - A.R. 41/63, 1791-1831 and undated (Box 151)
      - Sir William Henry Fremantle Papers, 1806-1814 and undated (Box 151)
    - Huntington Library (Box 151)
    - Public Record Office (Box 151)
    - Correspondence from Unidentified Sources, 1803-1854 (Box 151)
    - Miscellaneous Notes and Lists (Box 151)
    - Contents of Dropmore as Auctioned by Sotheby's in 1969 (Box 151)
  - Microfilm: (Box 152)
    Most of this microfilm, unlike that for Mississippi, is not duplicated by Xerox or other photographic copies. The sources of the film are: Boconnoc, the British Museum, the Public Record Office, the Bedfordshire Record Office, the Clements Library, the John Rylands Library, the Huntington Library, the Bodleian Library, and the Cleveland Public Library.
    - Reels 1-8 (Box 152)
    - Reels 9-16 (Box 153)
    - Reel 17 (Box 154)
  - Notes (arranged chronologically), 1700's-1900's (Box 155-158)
    Includes bibliography as well as notes taken upon manuscripts and printed sources.
- Mansfield Research
  Notes for a biography of William Murray, First Earl of Mansfield (1705-1793). These notes were made for Arthur T. Vanderbilt, who planned, but did not publish, a biography of Lord Mansfield.
  - Mansfield research notes (Box 159-160)
- Australia and New Zealand Research
  Descriptions, bibliographies, and notes on manuscripts and newspapers available at libraries in Canberra, Brisbane, Melbourne, South Australia, Tasmania, and at the Mitchell Library. Notes on politics in New Zealand date mostly during the 1870's, 1880's, and 1890's. Correspondence, 1957-1959. Reports on archives in Australia, 1952-1956.
  - Australia and New Zealand research notes (Box 161)
- Grand Juries Research
  Notes on grand juries, especially their presentments, in the United States, 18th-20th centuries.
  - Grand Juries research notes (Box 162)
- 1975 Accession, 18 boxes
  This accession was gifted to the University in 1975, and includes boxes 163-180. The materials from this accession were not interfiled with the rest of the collection. This series includes files pertaining to the William Baskerville Hamilton and Duke University subseries, alphabetical files on individuals, and Mississippi Research files.
  - Family Correspondence, Writings, Miscellaneous (Box 163)
  - Biographical Information, Estate Papers (Box 164)
  - Duke-Duke Press (Box 165)
  - Duke University: A-B (Box 166)
  - Duke University: Co (Box 167)
  - Duke Press-Graduate School (Box 168)
  - Alphabetical files: H-I (Box 169)
  - Alphabetical files: J-K (Box 170)
  - Alphabetical files: L-Mc (Box 171)
  - Alphabetical files: M-N (Box 172)
  - Alphabetical files: O-P (Box 173)
  - Alphabetical files: R (Box 174)
  - Alphabetical files: S (Box 175)
  - Alphabetical files: T-Y (Box 176)
  - History Courses Files (Box 177)
  - History Courses Files/Mississippi Research (Box 178)
  - Mississippi Research (Box 179)
  - British History Files (Box 180)
- British Manuscripts
  The following collections were donated by Professor Hamilton or his estate. They range in size from one or two items to several thousand. Each collection has its own catalog record.
  - 1. Anson, Charles V. (Box 180)
  - 2. Backhouse, John (Box 180)
  - 3. Balfour, Arthur James, 1st Earl of Balfour (Box 180)
  - 4. Bandinel Family (Box 180)
  - 5. Barrington, George William, Seventh Viscount Barrington (Box 180)
  - 6. Beaufort, Sir Francis (Box 180)
  - 7. Campbell, George Douglas, Eighth Duke of Argyll (Box 180)
  - 8. Cheesment-Severn, John (Box 180)
  - 9. Fane, John, Eleventh Earl of Westmorland (Box 180)
  - 10. Fazakerley, John Nicholas (Box 180)
  - 11. FitzRoy, Sir Almeric William (Box 180)
  - 12. Gladstone, William Ewart (Box 180)
  - 13. Godman, Miss (Box 180)
  - 14. Gore, Charles Alexander (Box 180)
  - 15. Grant, Sir William (1752-1832) (Box 180)
  - 16. Hall, Townsend Monckton (Box 180)
  - 17. Hart, Henry George (Box 180)
  - 18. Jones, Lloyd (Box 180)
  - 19. Labouchere, Henry, First Baron Taunton (Box 180)
  - 20. Lyttelton, William Henry, First Baron Lyttelton (Box 180)
  - 21. Napier, Sir Charles James (Box 180)
  - 22. Napier, Henry Edward (Box 180)
  - 23. Napier, Robert Cornelis, First Baron Napier of Magdala (Box 180)
  - 24. Neilson, George (Box 180)
  - 25. Noel-Buxton, Noel Edward, First Baron Noel Buxton (Box 180)
  - 26. Parliamentary Directory Questionnaire Responses (Box 180)
  - 27. Primrose, Sir Henry William (Box 180)
  - 28. Schindler, Sir Albert Houtum- (Box 180)
  - 29. Scrutton, Robert J. (Box 180)
  - 30. Sidney, Henry Marlow (Box 180)
  - 31. Smyth, Sir James Carmichael-, First Baronet (Box 180)
  - 32. Snelling, Rowland (Box 180)
  - 33. Talbot, Lady Margaret Jane (Stuart-Wortley) (Box 180)
  - 34. Trafford, Lionel James (Box 180)
  - 35. Wilson, James (Box 180)
  - 36. Wingate, Sir Francis Reginald, First Baronet (Box 180)
  - 37. Bisset, Robert (Box 180)
  - 38. Paget, Henry William, First Marquis of Anglesey (Box 180)
- Oversize Material
  - Miscellaneous Oversize (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Portrait, undated (Oversize-folder 1)